all right hello everyone and welcome
to another awaken from the meaning
crisis discord q a my name is brett
and we're here again with john verveigh
thanks john for being here
thanks for inviting me again it's
pleasure to be here
yeah well you're you're invite you have
a standing invitation so you're invited
anytime
but uh we have our we're back on track
now with our
our every two weeks uh uh q a
and uh everyone always looks forward to
these
so so i wanted to start off today we've
been having some
discussions in the discord uh about the
the four ps
and there's been some you know you know
some
discussion over what your exact
definitions
of perspectival knowing and
participatory knowing and really what
the difference is
between them and then so i i was
wondering if you could just clarify
your definitions for those two p's and
then i'd like to turn to
to mark and and and manual who have been
uh
playing around with uh with the four ps
themselves and maybe
uh they could talk a little bit about
what they've been playing with
uh and maybe get your your thoughts on
that
so sure i just want to interrupt here a
little bit so
if if we can get the reason for the
definition as well that would be great
what do you mean the justification for
the the definitions that what you mean
by the reason
well yeah like why it's important that
the definition is that way
sure sure okay so
um
there's many ways of trying to cut this
up i guess i'm trying to think of what's
a succinct way of doing it
so the idea of perspectival knowing is
based on the idea of knowing what it's
like to be here
now in this state of consciousness so
i know what it's like to be here now um
in my current state of consciousness in
my room
so i'm salience landscaping in a
particular way
and i have a sober state of mind i'm
sane
and so my salience landscaping is
unfolding in a particular way so
i know what it's like to be here now
um sober and that would be
a particular perspective and the reason
why i use perspectival knowing
is we we have we have this prevalent
metaphor
of this feature of salience landscaping
from a state of consciousness
like a perspective things things are
salient to me that seem in a way that's
centered on me both spatially
and temporally um it seems to be
something that i can modify
by sort of shifting how i'm framing
events
very much like an artistic perspective
so that's why
the term perspectival knowing is used
respectable knowing gives you a sense of
presence
that's what's sought after in video
games
and that sense of presence i would argue
reflects the fact
that you have a situational awareness
you're finding things salient here now
in a way that is efficacious or you
applying your skills or acquiring skills
that you do not have
um so in that sense
uh perspectival awareness is more basic
uh than procedural awareness since
procedural
knowing uh presupposes the perspective
of knowing
now respectable knowing is all about
salience landscaping how you're
sizing up situations getting a conscious
optimal grip on them
um so that you have a sense of presence
both of yourself
and the world that's another thing a
perspective does it makes things sort of
co-present
uh to each other participatory knowing
is
is a more primordial more basic form
uh part of the difficulty that people
have with this is many people carry sort
of in what's called an internalist view
of knowing
that to know something requires that you
know that you know it
there's been there's a lot of
philosophical arguments and evidence
that that can't be a defining feature of
knowledge
uh and this is what's led to its cons
what has become to be known as
externalism that there are many things
you know
without knowing that you know and in
fact you need you have to rely on that
presupposition even
even to bring up certain questions about
rationality and ethics i won't go into
those long arguments in detail
so participatory knowing is the kind of
knowing
that results from the way in which the
organism
and the environment are mutually shaped
to each other
so that affordances emerge affordances
are taken to be real relations
um and there's three there's sort of
three levels at which human beings
uh participate in that mutual shaping of
organism in world one of course is
biological
our evolutionary heritage has shaped our
environment and us to our environment
so that certain things are come out as
affordances to me certain
uh terrain features are walkable certain
things are graspable
certain certain things are visible to me
uh most of the electromagnetic spectrum
is not visible to me for example
um and that's that's known as niche
construction
um and then of course because we're
human beings we have culture
and what culture does is mutually shape
us to the environment and the
environment to you
so look around you you're in a room
probably i would
right so most of your environment has
been shaped
by tools to fit you but nevertheless you
also
have been uh shaped to fit that
environment
uh you wear clothes you learn right
certain
attitudes and behaviors etc the whole
process of enculturation
and then of course on top of that is and
i can't go into this in great detail i'm
just gonna
presume and i hope it's not too
presumptuous that people are aware of
what i'm talking about
there's the online there's the online
continual mutual shaping
um that's going on in relevance
realization
which is making which is sort of a
cognitive niche construction
so for example i have a mug here and i
pick up this mug
and part of it is right there's a
shaping of the
of the environments things of a certain
size and stability
and configuration are graspable by my
hand that's a real affordance
and then of course culture has shaped uh
this
object so that it's usable by me as a
tool and it'll also shape me
how to drink we have to learn how to do
this babies can't use mugs for example
and then of course right now there's my
online relevance realization
that is where i can use it to solve the
problems that i'm currently in
so all of that participatory knowing
that mutual shaping of self and world
creates a whole field of affordances for
me
of course most of those field most of
those affordances
are going unnoticed and unused by me
that wall over there right next to me i
could it's i can lean on it it's
leanable
but like you know i wasn't noticing that
or or
or or becoming aware of that until i
made it salient
so the perspectival knowing makes
salient
those affordances that are needed
to be actualized right now so the pers
the participatory knowing creates the
agent arena relationship opens up the
field of affordances
and this is important because without
that we'd just be hitting continual
combinatorial explosion
and then there's another layer this is
recursive relevance realization that i'm
talking about
on top of that is perspectival knowing
which does the salience landscaping it
makes certain affordances
salient to me and i get this sense of
presence
i get a situational awareness that
situational awareness
in turn affords me paying attention to
those patterns
to which i can apply my skills or from
which i can apply my skills
and then once i have a a a specific set
of skills
about social interaction and drawing
implications etc
then i get into propositional knowing
why do i
i do the why do i pick the the four i
pick
because i you can show dependency
relationships to them so there's a
causal justification
and there's a systematic relationship to
between them
which i just gave each one has
a uh a definable set of
um results and phenomenological
normativity
propositional knowing works in terms of
beliefs that produce theories that give
us a sense of conviction
procedural knowing works in terms of
sensory motor interactions that produce
a sense
of power um
perspectival knowing as i said uh works
in terms of perspective
perspective salience landscaping that
gives us a sense
a presence and guides our situational
awareness
and the participatory knowing as i said
gives us affordances
when we get a phenom and it's not needed
but when we have a phenomenological
awareness
of participatory knowing it's usually in
terms of the way
it is ramifying through the other kinds
of knowing and that we have a sense of
belonging we have a sense that
the the propositional
is plugging well into the procedural is
plugging well into the participatory
that's plugging well
into our environment with effective
recursive relevance realization
so each one have has a different
phenomenological normativity
the first results in theories the second
results and skills the third results
in perspective and then the fourth
results in
you know agent arena relationships
and so i guess that's enough for now
there's i mean i have a lot more to say
about all of this but
my basic justification for that is i can
tell you what is known
like knowing that knowing how knowing
what it's like etc
i can tell you what it results in i can
result
i can tell you it's normative condition
and i can show you
the principled relationships of
causation and dependence between them
so i mean like any taxonomy it's
justified
by its cleanness its distinctiveness
its coherence etc so that's my basic
argument
in kind of a nutshell all right
thank you for that i'm going to have to
listen to that again a few times and
then i'll so i i i i've given a recent
version of
this at uh the movement summit um and it
was recorded as a talk
and i got a lot of positive feedback on
that and so
uh rafe kelly who organizes summit is is
right now that talk is behind a paywall
but it is going to be released to the
general public soon
well great so mark and manuel did you
want to
to present what you were thinking of now
or did you want to
think about his response and do it next
time what did you what did you want to
do
well i'm uh i'm fresh off explaining
this earlier today so i think
i think we can give it another go and a
better go based on uh
based on some sort of stuff that we that
we
talked about today with somebody um
so john one of the things we've been
working on and a lot of people have
contributed
you know andre and emmanuel and i have
been working very close on this and a
bunch of other people and
probably too many to name so i apologize
that i can't name everybody i mean nick
nick helped us tremendously with a lot
of this work
so i i'm doing a lot of reverse
engineering
right from the perspective of somebody
who doesn't have a meeting crisis
and didn't really realize that people
could because why i fixed mine
like what's wrong with all you so um
so that that's one of the reasons why i
really resonated with like jordan
peterson and then and then of course
your work which is uh which is
you know a much broader in in scope with
the
with the whole science of the meaning
crisis and the framework to talk about
it
which is very helpful when you're trying
to help other people uh to get out of
this meaning crisis thing that
that you know you don't really have a
good handle on so
one of the problems that i think we
recognized was that in order for the
things
to in order to do the things i think
would work from my reverse engineered
perspective
i needed to uh to reconceive of a few
things
and a bunch of people like i said help
help to sort of figure out
where the missing pieces were in some
sense and
what we came to was something like the
perspectival seems to be wrapped up in
all the types of knowing
and so from from our perspective
it seems like it's a deeper structure
right because in order to know anything
you have to know it in relation to
something
and the thing that handles relations in
general
is your framing device which is roughly
coming from your perspectival
uh system and then
the features that we think that the
perspectival system has in particular
are are things like
flexibility and that's probably
missing in some people and we conceive
of it as a capacity
and so maybe it gets tired for example
right like maybe you're just your
perspectival capacity goes down during
the day or something
it's probably true of the types of
knowing as well but
you kind of need that perspective first
before
a piece of information can be knowledge
in some sense
because because that has to come first
in order to provide the the information
a frame to be to be relevant
in any fashion and if that's true
and it's a capacity and it has
flexibility
then this explains a bunch of things
about why people
are unable to engage at certain levels
so a lot of people seem to be what i
call perspectivally stuck
yes and then there's some people that
seem to be
perspectively broken right like they you
explain something to them about their
perspective that's obviously wrong
and they can't they can't get there in
some sense
and so when we made that move
it sort of left a hole and the at the
same time the other line of reasoning
was something like
well you know we've got the we've got
the
the propositional and the way you
navigate the propositional space
seems to have something to do with
procedural
yes and i've conceived of the procedural
as
not not exclusively but maybe at its
base level logic reason and rationality
and one of the things i've noticed about
uh about uh the procedural
is that if you pick a starting point
and your propositions are set your
ending point is guaranteed
so it's a very safe space to operate in
in some sense because you can build a
knowable world or a knowable perspective
and as long as you use those two tools
you can know the whole thing at least in
theory
uh and and that gives you a great deal
of safety and i think that's part and
parcel to the to the meaning crisis in
some sense
and then and then of course we're
mapping all this on the sides of the
brain
and and and i'm sort of conceiving as
those two as discrete processing
of signals so if they were signals if
the ways of knowing were more signal
types
they would be getting sampled discretely
on that side
and then on the other side we have no
issue with
participatory we think that's fine um
it seems it seems good but the
the thing that comes up is what there's
no navigational skill
with the participatory like it's just a
movement right it's just the ability to
to go around a space in some sense and
and interact with things
but the interaction doesn't tell you
whether or not it's right or wrong
and so we kind of figured we needed more
of a compass in that space
and then what we came at independently
and then realized
that mary cohen had already come to this
was this parabolic way of knowing
but our our justification for parabolic
knowing
is something like this is where
symbol and metaphor
uh come into play right and parables in
particular so
story fragments things like that and
those are sort of the base structures
that give you the ability
to do participation with the special
sort of added feature that um that they
have
at least one way sort of in
and but usually multiple ways sort of in
and then multiple exit points
and so you can take those chunks and
sort of apply them in different
situations
and and or in different perspectives and
and
and you still have a choice of changing
how it ends
so you can find yourself in the same
situation but not
end up at the same result even though
you have exactly the same landscape and
tool set
so that was sort of our justification
for for the parabolic way of knowing
and and why we think it's important and
then the parabolic would also
hold things like like uh would also be
involved
with things like memes although we have
a whole space for
for means now but but but what do you
what do you what are your first
impressions of that sort of a model
well there was a lot there so i'll try
to respond to many points
going in um uh first of all
i i have a concern about confusing
language or training and language of
explaining here
i think that the perspective of knowing
often comes first although not always um
in
when we try to train train or intervene
um so it would seem in that way that all
the other kinds of knowing are dependent
on it but if you
if you talk about uh causal um
the for example the relevance
realization machinery is deeper than
your conscious awareness and makes it
possible
there's all kinds of unconscious
processing going on it's doing that
mutual shaping and participation
that actually makes consciousness
possible but you have to be careful are
you talking about order
in terms of accessibility of training or
order in
uh in order an
explanation of causation
so i would want to make clear i would
be worried about making claims about
patterns by which we want to intervene
as being
directly mappable on patterns in the
ontology of the four kinds of knowing
and so uh that's why i was i i don't
make the perspectival the most
foundational because
it causally can't be
because you know if i if i mess up
certain areas of your brain that are
processing unconsciously
that will massively affect your
perspectival knowing outside
of your self-awareness etc etc um
so i think that
part of what you're putting your finger
on though is that we need to
do you think we need to keep the those
two ways of thinking about the four
kinds of knowing distinct
but we need to talk about the difference
between
the causal relationship between them
and the way we need to talk about them
in order to train them
you know and i use the examples of the
language you use to train uh
memory is a perspectival thing you use
the memory palace but that doesn't mean
that that's how we actually participate
in our memory our memory doesn't work
that kind of perspectival fashion at all
um and so the training language and the
explaining language
they have to be kept clearly um distinct
and not confused
but i do think that you're making an
important point i would say
um about more work needs to be done
relating
um that explaining language to the
training language
um yeah i hadn't thought about that
enough i'm just sort of reflecting on
this right now
it's a so there's a difference between
explaining and giving people the right
tools for intervening and of course
respectable knowing is going to seem
like it's the first because when we're
trying to intervene on people
we're relying to a significant degree on
their self-awareness which is located
in the prospective knowing so that makes
sense to me
so how do we how do we manage that
that's
i don't know i i got to think about this
this is a this is a really important
question
about the participatory knowing so uh
the idea is
is that narrative is a way in which we
actually bridge between all the kinds of
knowing that was my response to mary
that in narrative uh we use propositions
uh to talk about interactions procedural
in order to get people's points of view
in order
to ultimately talk about how people's
identities are changed
and that's the whole point of narrative
narrative gives us a temporally extended
self
it opens up the scope in which the
mutual shaping between
uh agent and arena works that's why we
have to teach narrative to people
we have to teach them and teach them and
practice it and practice it and practice
it
because what it does is it actually
integrates the four kinds of knowing in
a particular way
and affords extending the
agent arena relationship the world is
opened up and the
scope of agencies opened up that's why
of course you don't expect
four-year-olds to engage
in the long-term planning that you would
expect 40-year-olds to engage in
etc so not i'm not
i i don't think therefore of uh the
parabolic
as a separate kind of knowing the the
problem is when you start to define
uh the kinds of knowing into in terms of
the products produced you're going to
get a proliferation of kinds of knowing
because then you're going to get
scientific knowing you're going to get
symbolic knowing
right you're going to get historical
knowing
you're going to get all different kinds
of knowing and so that's one of the
problems i brought up with mary that's
why i tried to limit
the kinds of knowing to the functions
performed
and the the uh normative
standards we use in order to evaluate it
so
i think but that you see that makes it
all the more important the fact that
it's not its separate kind of knowing
means it's precisely important
uh i would argue because symbolic
narrative kind of knowing is a way in
which
we we basically integrate and mediate
between the different kinds of knowing
that's why it's very hard to talk about
symbolic knowing
without invoking propositional or
procedural or perspectival or
participatory
um because think about it when you're
reading a narrative you say where's the
participatory narrative well of course
there's
your perspectival but you also get you
know you get the mirroring function you
get a weird
i identity relation forming uh when you
listen to narrative or watch narrative
so all of those things have to be in
play in order for
uh what mary called the parabola
could you just give a descript an
explanation of definition of parabolic
for
for those who don't know oh so what mary
mary was arguing that uh
that if i when i i'm just all i know is
her her version of it uh she described
parabolic knowing
as knowing by sort of means of symbols
and metaphors um
so um she gave the example of the the
way i use
family relationships uh to understand
the relationship between cutlery
so what we do is we map one system onto
another um and and then
sort of try to say well all knowing is a
mapping function
and so we can't make the mapping
function itself a kind of knowing
because of all knowing makes use of
mapping functions that would be a
category mistake
then it was sort of well she said yeah
but you're sort of mapping
uh between you know uh
domains in a way that provokes insight
and then again i s you know but insight
is possible in all kinds of knowing so
you don't want to make insight its own
kind of knowing
so i think
it's better to see metaphor and symbol
as a narrative as ways that bridge
between
the kinds of knowing and that therefore
afford
understanding which is to more properly
grasp
the relations of relevance between
kinds of knowing when i really
understand something i know
i know i don't just have propositional
knowledge and procedural
and perspectival and participatory i
what i have is i grasp the significance
the relations of relevance between the
kinds of knowing that's
that's why you can really get to know uh
you know when we when we think we really
understand somebody
we we don't know them we don't have just
beliefs about them
or even skills about them or even you
know experience of them
uh we or even a binding of identity with
them
we we have a sense among how all of
those fit together
mutually support each other and so i
think of
metaphor as a profound way of aligning
the four kinds of knowledge
to bring about understanding the reason
i rely on that distinction is because
there's an increasing distinction
coming out of the philosophy of science
between distinguishing between
between knowledge which is the grasping
of propositions or
the having of a skill and understanding
which is to grasp the significance or
relevance of what you know
and again you don't want to reduce the
understanding to knowledge because then
you won't be able to
explain either knowledge or
understanding if you just simply equate
the two
sorry that was a very long arg a very
long answer
mark um so i think
i think your intuition that the symbolic
gives you powerful
access the participatory
from the procedural the propositional
and the perspective is exactly right but
i think it gives you access precisely
because it's the kind of knowing
that bridges between it's right it's
it's
sorry it's not a kind of knowing that's
what i'm arguing it's a kind of way of
bridging between the kinds of knowing so
they could they can more mutually access
each other
when the kinds of knowing or mutually
access each other
that's what we mean by understanding
so i i i just want to get a couple sting
straight so that we're all on the same
page
so the the way you conceived of the ways
of knowing is is that privileging
phenomenology
is is that where you're straight it's
not privileged
nominology as a methodology it's
privileging i guess
um do you mean phenomenology as a
discipline or phenomenological
experience which do you mean by well
yeah like
phenomenological experience right so
that it's it's graspable from a
phenomenological
perspective uh
i
don't think that's what i i think i
maybe i wasn't i want to make sure that
i'm not um
being obtuse and i stated at the
beginning that i don't
think all kinds of knowing have to be
from an internalist perspective
that there's externalist kinds of
knowing especially participatory
that was my saying that not all knowing
has to be
directly phenomenologically accessible
to us
as a phenomenological experience per se
so and of course there's there's senses
in which you don't directly you don't
have a direct phenomenological awareness
of your skills or of the machinery
that's generating the affordances
the phenomenological experiencing
experience actually privile
presupposes not privileges supposes
all of those processes at work to
generate
its intelligibility
right okay
in the conversation with mary cohen you
mentioned
that the
the the choice of the framework was
fairly arbitrary and that
its justification is by its explanatory
power right
it's cleanness its coherence its ability
to match up with the way
these terms are used you know in other
disciplines
that's what i mean by explanatory power
i don't just mean sort of
ad-hoc pragmatic explanatory power i
mean that in a broad
you know in in a more epistemological
sense but yeah
i mean there is there is there is no
other way of justifying a taxonomy
as far as i can tell
yeah i just i just wanted to uh i i did
leave something out actually it was a
piece that
that that andre talked about it just
there's a lot of pieces right so
um the the one observation that andre in
particular made was that
you know the perspectival capacity
would have to interact with the types of
knowing
uh you know bi-directionally right so
they're both informing each other in
some sense
and the reason why we think this
actually works better and maps better is
something like
if you if you take a hallucinogenic drug
like you drop some acid or something
and you have what we're calling the
profound experience right
but you take nothing back with you it's
like well what happened there well the
first thing that happened is that
you decided you you made a decision to
to imagine a perspective and then you
decided that
uh to adopt that perspective and then
you decided
that you know you were going to try to
participate in that
perspective actively right and then
and then you have the the participation
and now
when you unwind all of that what happens
is
you can get all the way to the end and
say yeah whatever happened to me
is great but i'm not going to take
anything back with me right i'm not
going to integrate
i'm just going to have that experience
and like maybe
not pretend like it didn't happen
because there are lots of options but
one option would be pretend like that
didn't happen to me
and that explains a whole bunch of
psychological phenomena
having that that extra layer in there
and one way that might happen
is if you had an experience and one of
your ways of knowing
was somehow malfunctioning or damaged it
would look
like your perspectival capacity was
damaged
but i would argue that because the
perspective has to happen first in order
for knowledge to exist in some sense not
not
facts or experiences or phenomena but
knowledge because it requires a frame to
be discernable
and to be meaningful then it would look
like a
perspectival problem when in fact it was
a problem with the knowledge system
but what that also means is it gives you
especially if you're using a signaling
model and you're assuming that the four
types of knowing are basically just
signals
and they're combining somehow right it
gives you this really powerful model to
explain why we see the same
end phenomena with completely different
uh source you know sources for the
problem
um and and that was that was sort of
part of that
uh decision and then you know the
it with respect to the parabolic you
know
i still i still prefer this navigational
model that we don't have otherwise
you know just because you have a
perspective what do you mean by
navigational you mean navigating through
participatory knowing navigating through
the world navigating through
participatory knowing and through the
world
right because again you've got the
procedural that can navigate
for you the propositions but the
procedural can't navigate
your participation because your
participation is in some clear sense
continuous
right and so there's this idea of
continuous and discrete sampling on top
of this
and the reason why that's important is
because you you know like if you're
on a bike you're constantly balancing
right and so
you know it's not clear to me how you
would know to balance and how you would
know
as you're going through the world
actively that you know
in terms of procedures
what that
so there mark you have far more options
okay so let me try and address a couple
things um
one is i i
i was always clear that i got the
and i thought i i was i was indicated
of course all the all the kinds of
knowing can have causal impact on each
other
um that um
if i was trying maybe i was
maybe when i was talking about causal
dependence
that was being understood as indicating
there's only a one-way
causal interaction um what's that
supposed to show as an ontological
dependence it's it's that there can't be
proposition
you you could have just sort of
participatory knowing on its own which
i i think that's what microbes have
um right and you and then you might get
a beginning of sense making as you get a
little bit higher
um and then you when you get a capacity
for learning you're going to get
procedural
and only when you have something like
language are you going to get
propositional
so the ontological dependence means
like what is which which ones perceive
which ones presuppose the other for
their existence
but that is not to say that they are are
causally independent from each other
of course and that's what i meant by
intervention i think uh perspectival
knowing is one of the most powerful ways
you can intervene
on on your participatory knowing that's
what in fact happens
when you get things like you know
loneliness
or you get culture shock because your
salience landscaping
isn't working and that sends error
signal
i think to your participatory knowing
and it starts to uh self-organize
again language of training is the
language of causal interaction the
language of explaining is the language
of ontological dependence
right uh so my being able to see
dependent on my being alive i can be
alive without being able to see
but my being able to see causality
interacts with me being alive because
seeing allows me to get food and eat
there's a difference between things
being able to causally interact
and then being causally dependent one is
trying to get sort of the ontological
structure
that's causal dependence you're trying
to train of course you're trying to see
well how can they impact and intervene
on each other
so i i never meant to exclude
a bi-directionality of causal
interaction between the kinds of knowing
in fact i think the kinds of knowing
impact and constrain each other all over
the place
it wasn't the point of of the taxonomy
as
as i've been trying to sort of say i
think the point of the taxonomy is to
explain and the point of explanation is
to reveal ontological structure
and ontological structure works in terms
of causal dependence
primarily now the
point about the parabolic i i get what
you're saying
about how we navigate and and i thought
i was agreeing with that let me tell you
what how why i thought that i think the
primary
way in which we you'll allow me to
metaphor
navigate uh participatory knowing
navigate the
the transformation of
the agent arena relationship is the
process of aspiration and the aspiration
can ultimately
lead to reciprocal opening etc etc then
i do think that the act of aspiration
and that's what i try to argue
depends on narrative's ability to open
the temporal skills
i mean what narrative allows me to do is
take my current self
identify with my future self and that
identity is non-logical
and that's what i need for aspiration
and that's inherently symbolic
so i do think that narrative
symbolism are the primary tools we use
for aspiration and i think aspiration
is the process by which we navigate
participatory
by which we restructure the agent arena
relationship that's why
i've been spending a lot of time on this
uh notion of aspiration and i do think
parabolic uh thinking
in mary's sense narrative symbolic
thinking
is necessary for
um aspiration i do think ultimately the
kind of
knowing that's involved right the way
you
you know yourself by identifying with
yourself it's ultimately a form of
participatory knowing
um i don't know if that's answering your
question
but i i i'm glad you asked it because
never meant to convey that the
ontological relationships of dependents
were some uh were meant to be some kind
of
unidirectional line of causal
interaction
so that's why i gave you the metaphor of
sight and being alive
sight depends on being alive being alive
doesn't depend on sight
but seeing and being alive of course
causally interact
and affect each other um and so
so i i i i i think i i guess
that that's my fault to some degree i i
didn't
i haven't taken the time to
really clarify like pulling out the
language of explaining the language of
explaining distinguishing
the causal interaction that is really
central for training
from the causal dependence that's really
central for
explaining and i like i said i do think
um there is a
but again i didn't i
i'm frustrated with myself because i it
was so i i
you're right i have never explicitly
argued that
i i said that aspiration is how we we
uh transformed the agent in a
relationship but i've never directly
explicitly said
that's the primary function that
transforms participatory knowing
um and it and and for and i agree with
mary i think that's inherently narrative
um and inherently symbolic it has to be
because we're we're
we're trying to a participatory knowing
that's
based on non-logical identity and so
that's going to be narrative and
symbolic in nature
um
i don't know if i'm disagreeing with
mary i just i like i said
again it depends
depends what you want what would you
gain by
adding that as a new kind of knowing um
what would be what would be what would
be like what in
what aspect like does it have its own
particular phenomenological normativity
what does what does what does parabolic
knowing result in i know what
propositional procedural perspectival
and participatory result in and i know
what their respective
senses of normativity are i i can't get
that for
so i don't know how to fit parabolic
knowing into the taxonomy because it
doesn't i can't give answers to the
principles
by which the taxonomy was produced
right yeah no i i i was uh explaining uh
perspectival with
with respect to the fact that it
interacts with the types of knowing
in in and i'll argue in a unique way uh
specifically because you called that out
and said oh you can you know damage this
and it looks like they're perspectively
broken
but i would argue that that's not what
you damaged you damaged the type of
knowing
and or or they lost access to a bunch of
of knowledge that they had
and that constrains the the perspective
and i can see why it would look the
other way around
um and and there would be no way to tell
right that's part of the downside
and then i would say you know that the
parabolic is all about
how you understand the relationship
between objects
that's what you get out of it to mary's
point this whole idea about
uh about square and circle and how they
represent
you know male and female and and all of
that
is the way we understand narrative and
but those are multi-affordable
ways of navigating your participation
with the world
is is something like what i'm what i'm
arguing there and because i'm not
getting rid of the perspectival i'm just
making it primary
uh you know nothing much is changing
we're just adding a bunch of stuff that
looks like it might be
useful and um i'm part of the way
through a paper
and then manuel's added a bunch of stuff
uh that we're gonna put in and so we'll
we'll get you a paper and maybe that'll
help clear up what we're thinking and
how well but but also i mean
you guys are free to do what you want i
mean you just i'm just answering your
questions i mean
i'm not i'm not claiming authority over
you right uh like right
and and then also how i'm also happy uh
to uh you know enter into ongoing
dialogue
with you that that's that's what this is
about um
so i hope i didn't convey anything
inappropriate here that's not what
not at all okay no i just wanted to make
it clear that
we can explain this better and written
so that you'll have more time to chew on
it and we're in the process of doing
that
and we're happy to do it okay well
that's great and i'm happy to do that
um and perhaps what we've accomplished
right now
is i i've tried to i've tried to be very
clear
about you know the principles behind my
methodology and the justification
and and the distinctions that i think uh
uh prevent certain kinds of confusion
um and so
i i it would be helpful if if if
if you guys responded in kind along
those lines
that fair yeah that sounds fair john
thank you
i appreciate the time and the care
you've taken no no no
this is this is i mean this is really
good also because
uh i mean and of course that's going to
happen
i i i mean maybe i'll revise what i have
to say
substantially in a theoretical sense but
even if i don't
uh i i i see that there's these
there's sort of holes in my work that
have been revealed in this discussion um
i i feel responsible for now and
responsible too
um and and so that's very very helpful
to me
very very helpful i i mean a little bit
caught between
wearing two hats the hats of a cognitive
scientist in the hat of somebody
sort of trying to help people train
skills and interventions and so
i'm trying to manage between those uh
right now sorry i talked over somebody i
apologize
yeah i was just gonna say that we're
under the impression that we resolved
those holes for ourselves
so yeah right maybe
you might benefit from that couldn't
quite hear the last thing you said i'm
sorry
uh well maybe you might benefit from
from our ideas right and how to fill the
holes
i'm sure i will i i mean i've i've
already have
and i'm um yeah
but yeah i i'm happy to see what you
have written
and to respond in depth so so this has
been fantastic
and taken some time but i think time
very well spent
but let's try to get let's try to get
some some questions in from
from some others uh tyler got missed
last week at the end so
tyler why don't you go ahead
hello john welcome
good to hear from you too um
yeah i i just caught i think your
comment on the
um the participatory framing of uh
like microbial life and that's really
fascinating i love the way that
i love the way it's set up in a in a
stack right like you have this kind of
integration right in motion but it's
really fascinating because i
i actually think of it um like if i step
outside of the human framing for a
moment and i look at the
what's actually happening on the globe
is it like a giant cybernetic organism
it's almost like
each organism is in fact a proposition
right
it's some element of searching
the you know whatever the design space
is for survival
and that you can yeah like unpack the uh
the genetic expression
and like fully express that proposition
that's really
um yeah so that's kind of how i see it
as like as
maybe at the flipping the stack there
but that's interesting i mean that goes
towards the
the this idea again about um
there's a lot but the that goes towards
the idea that there's a logos that's
well this is what i would say uh tyler
that uh
the notion of logos as intelligibility
that there's a logos that's
non-propositional but it's still
properly logos
um so a greek way of talking about
something like the genetic code of
course is it's not a proposition
um but it is it is it is some kind of
code
um that um organizes and constrains
things
in a reliable and discriminate
and in discriminating fashion
of course we have to be careful when we
talk about dna as a code
because it's originally meant as a
metaphor and we can get caught up in it
a little too much
um oh sure well i mean there's that
other additional layer on top though
like the
additional genetic code itself of the
triplicate
expression that that that in itself
totally totally
and so i think i think the notion of
and i think that's what's interesting
about logos because logos
and that's why i like it as a term
because
intelligibility because logos to my mind
uh
and this sort of a sort of a
heideggerian reading
right logos to my mind points to that
stacking
uh that i was talking about because you
know it means speech but it also means
gathering things together so they belong
together
and it also means a sense of that and
then it also
ultimately uh means some deeper pattern
or real pattern in the world
that affords all of that happening all
right like
sorry it's just like the proper pushing
of that information through the stack
right it's it's yeah and then that
constant self-expression and
self-testing and
reintegration with the uh the
environment at least in terms of the
organization
um my my question from last time and
that just
came in at the end and missed it but um
it has to do with the expression of the
feminine
in these spaces yeah it seems to me that
the crux of a lot of this meaning crisis
who has a lack of general capacity
which is kind of foundational to life
right life is
generative so yes i'm wondering in
like so i even switched my name as a
kind of uh nod to it but
i i'm wondering in the hypostasis like
in the expression of the essence of
nature and how we conceive of it
in the father the son and the holy
spirit where is
how is it that we're receiving the
divine feminine is that expressing
itself and
where where is it is it hiding like is
is that in fact the kind of inverted
weird nature of it that it is always
hidden and you have to go searching for
it
yeah yeah sorry can you comment on that
perhaps well first of all i think that's
important
oh and you know i've met with the board
of the verveiki foundation and you know
i i have had it
as a policy pre-existing all of this
that
i have tried to encourage
that the feminine voice and one of
things i wanted is
not to equate the feminine with just
women or the masculine with just men
but i did i i want more women
participating in all of this for exactly
the reasons
that you articulate i think i mean the
evidence is i think
mounting that we work better in
distributed cognition
and i i would i would predict that we'll
find
that we work better uh when we have you
know
some distribution i don't know what it
is
but that might be an empirical question
and not just a moral question
you know what what did distribution of
feminine
and masculine i i i prefer yin and yang
because it doesn't get so politically
laden but anyway within
um distributed cognition i think that's
that's very right i think our culture is
overly yang
i was talking with jp morseau about this
it's going to be released on voices with
raviki and how
um christianity got especially talked
about
the idea that it got very to something
we got very locked down in top down
emanation
and it's lost um the bottom-up
emergence from the so-called material
world
what's interesting is a lot of the
thinkers that
jp and i were talking about um
scottish aerogena but even there's even
aspects of this in aquinas
you can see them as trying to get more
of a balance but especially aerogena
between the top down emanation
and the the bottom-up emergence
and and what was interesting is that
regina did this work on
trying to see creation as something that
really integrates in the dialect fashion
the bottom up
generativity of emergence and then the
top-down
selectivity of emanation
and i think that that's the right way to
go
that's why paying attention to
dialectical thinkers not dialectic just
in their manner but
that they they ultimately saw the
ontology as dialectical in its very
nature
i think that and the fact that
there's more and more this is what jp
was claiming there's more and more
current
christian thinkers who are turning that
way i think this is all a way
of trying to make space and a proper
place
for the feminine within
our ontology that goes much deeper
and i think is therefore in some sense
more important than all the political
discourse around that
yeah i can say i i i think i agree
very much so with that uh i appreciate
it john thank you
thank you and so by the way tyler
that sort of goes to the previous
discussion
like that's why you sometimes you can
you can sometimes hear it in my voice i
do i do want to respond because
you know because i have these arguments
and ideas because they bring clarity
and that's a very sort of top-down
selective thing but i don't want to
strangle
if you if i don't i don't want to
strangle the bottom-up emergence
that's happening in the discord server
right and so
i i that's what i meant about i find it
tricky to wear these two hats
and and moderate between them so
i i i'm asking for people's um
patience and good faith because i i want
to keep
uh i want to keep in deep dialogue with
the community and
and i want to i i want to help
election and clarification but i really
don't want to strangle
that generativity that that bottom up
emergence
because um it's gonna it's gonna uncover
and realize things that i could not
possibly do
and it's gonna shape things that are
more relevant to responding to the
meaning crisis
that i could not do as any kind of
individual
so you said was actually
running through what was going on in the
previous discussion at least as sort of
a
a sense of attitude of orientation in my
in my thinking yeah i agree
yeah and it's one thing that i've kind
of been drawn to
uh because i believe it is important and
anyone that is expressing that or
who is expressing the importance of it i
think their signal should be boosted
and that this is um it's absolutely
seems to be expressed at the
sociological level right and
and uh and the individuals certainly
here have been reported anecdotally so
yeah there's something deeply um
incongruous right now between the
expression of the masculine and the
feminine the yin and the yang
and i i'm i'm all for uh getting that
thing to swirl back into unity
right oh well yeah i think you and i are
deep
in deep agreement about this um
so i mean it's a tricky thing because
we're we're plugging into the
perennial problem of trying to move
between plasticity and stability
much plasticity and the system breaks
down too much stability
and the system becomes fragile and
breaks um
and so trying to to constantly adjust
that sweet spot
is is very very challenging oh it is
huge
there but there's okay but it feels like
there could be an attractor of some kind
that's uniquely it's like it's the third
element right
it's the it's triplicate form because we
get stuck in this binary sense of
masculine
feminine too but we have to recognize
the transformative
and the transformative is only possible
with the triplicate structure so
we we have to recognize
i i don't know there's something deeper
even than that and that has to do with
the participatory for sure
like right now right like what what
people engage in and truly appreciate
with
with what it is to interact in that
sense and so there's
there's something missing in our current
environment and in our current
conversational space that represents
an equal attractor for both the
masculine and feminine and we're getting
close i
i i i touch on it every now and then
let's say but
yeah there's a whole constellation of
topics it's more like an orchestration
of conversations than one
right yeah there's something going on
yeah
i i think there are many of these uh
i think there's the mask and then the
feminine or the yin and yang
like i said i think there is finding
this
like i said which is tricky finding this
sweet spot that
you know allows flow without fusion or
confusion between
languages of training and languages of
explaining and
uh and and also getting something also
between
individuation and participation there's
all of these
sort of you know binaries um
that we are trying to
you allow me the metaphor we're trying
to i see myself at least and
most people are interested in my work i
i see myself as trying to set them into
motion again
to get them dynamically dialectic again
and so that as you as you call it
and you know chris knight also called
that artwork
that that third factor um the logo
starts to appear again
um so that that's been driving
a driving concern and goal of my work
oh oh yeah
it's perfect i had to talk with uh
forest landry it was
fantastic and i will echo my agreement
with jordan that you absolutely need to
speak with me
if you haven't already um yeah oh
maybe i'll just reach out to him cold
call then
you never met him so it's kind of okay
right right yeah we're trying to
orchestrate it
um i i think it i think would be very
valuable
his book imminent metaphysics is uh it's
it's
i'm i'm gaining a great deal of insight
and clarity
i i'd be happy to talk with forest very
much
fantastic all right thanks so much john
i don't want to take up any more time i
really appreciate it so so i think okay
we didn't quite get to uh to to our
our our list of questions today but i
think it's been a great uh
a great discussion and an important you
know link between
the discord server and the talks that go
on here and
and the work that you do john
uh i'm like i said i'm trying to i'll
pick up mark's
metaphor because i think it's really
appropriate here and to also
show the importance of it as he's
indicated i i i'm trying to learn how to
navigate
um this and so
i really appreciate uh
cordiality and and and and sort
and and and the sense of um
working together fellowship um i really
appreciate it here and
um i hope that i am doing
i'm doing a lot to reciprocate that with
people
um i've been i've convinced concern that
i've been a little bit too didactic
uh tonight and so i hope that didn't
come across
i think this has been great and and
apologies to those who didn't get to ask
questions but next time
we will put you at the top of the list
so so
we'll get there but again i i think
these i think it you know we have these
as q and a's but i think it's important
and if if those of you in the server
have have
ideas that you've been working on and
you want to spend a little bit of time
on them at the beginning of these q and
a's you can let me know as well i think
it's important that we do this
this is a great opportunity for us to
have these these conversations
i agree with that so
thank you again john uh thank you uh
to mark emmanuel and andre and everyone
who has been
working on on the four or five ps uh
here in the server and
and thanks to everyone being here and
and listening this has been
fantastic i really appreciate uh your
time
well thank you everyone i really
appreciate
how the
the caliber of the questions is is
is is constantly improving and
probative and how creative they are
so i i thank you for i think all of you
for that especially
you know uh uh mark and emmanuel and
and andre and and also tyler it was it
was excellent thank you very much guys
all right thanks everyone have a great
night
okay take care everyone stay safe
good night john hey thank you